<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Salientia Stuff - Word of the Week</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/feeds/word-of-the-week.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://yvanhuele.github.io/</id><updated>2018-04-24T22:30:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Управление</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/upravlenie.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-24T22:30:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-04-24T22:30:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-04-24:/upravlenie.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Out of Control&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's featured word is управление, the Russian word for administration, direction, or control, because no matter how hard I try, I can't seem to avoid learning about languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I was watching one of the lecture videos recorded for a &lt;a href="http://rll.berkeley.edu/deeprlcourse/"&gt;course on deep reinforcement …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Out of Control&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's featured word is управление, the Russian word for administration, direction, or control, because no matter how hard I try, I can't seem to avoid learning about languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I was watching one of the lecture videos recorded for a &lt;a href="http://rll.berkeley.edu/deeprlcourse/"&gt;course on deep reinforcement learning at Berkeley&lt;/a&gt;. While explaining the basic terminology, the professor explained there are &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/C_LGsoe36I8?t=11m30s"&gt;two common notations for states and actions&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"In most of this class [...] I'm going to use 's' to denote states and 'a' to denote actions. This kind of notation was popularized with the introduction of dynamic programming by Richard Bellman in the 1950s, and it makes a lot of sense because S is the first letter of state in the English language and A is the first letter of the word action. Those of you that have maybe more of a robotics or control background [...] might notice a slightly different notation where the letter 'x' is used to denote state and 'u' is used to denote action. This kind of notation was popularized in optimal control with work by folks like Lev Pontryagin. This kind of notation also makes sense because X is the letter that's often used to denote an unknown variable and U is the first letter for the word action in Russian, управление."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is not the first time knowledge of foreign languages has been foisted upon me when I was quietly minding my own business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Escape from the Lavatorial&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first encounter with the Cyrillic alphabet was through the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tate%E2%80%93Shafarevich_group"&gt;Tate-Shafarevich group&lt;/a&gt;, which plays an important role in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birch_and_Swinnerton-Dyer_conjecture"&gt;Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer (BSD) Conjecture&lt;/a&gt;, one of the most important open problems in number theory. The Cyrillic letter &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sha_(Cyrillic)"&gt;Ш (Sha)&lt;/a&gt; is commonly used to denote the Tate-Shafarevich group. For example, in John Tate's famous description of the BSD conjecture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"This remarkable conjecture relates the behavior of a function &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(L\)&lt;/span&gt; at a point where it is not at present known to be defined to the order of a group &lt;span class="math"&gt;\(Ш\)&lt;/span&gt; which is not known to be finite."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(&lt;a href="https://eudml.org/doc/142261"&gt;pg 198 of &lt;em&gt;The Arithmetic of Elliptic Curves&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of Ш to denote the Tate-Shafarevich group was introduced by J.W.S. Cassels. In &lt;em&gt;Lectures on Elliptic Curves&lt;/em&gt;, Cassels makes the following remark in a footnote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"This is the author's most lasting contribution to the subject. The original notation was TS, which, Tate tells me, was intended to continue the lavatorial allusion of WC [Weil–Châtelet group]. The Americanism "tough shit" indicates the part that is difficult to eliminate."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you don't use Ш to denote the Tate-Shafarevich group, there's still some hidden information contained in the name. A &lt;a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/19987/math-paper-authors-order"&gt;common convention in mathematics&lt;/a&gt; is to list authors in alphabetical order. Lavatorial acronyms aside, I've heard the following justification for putting Tate's name first: Though &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; comes before &lt;em&gt;T&lt;/em&gt; in the Roman alphabet, &lt;em&gt;Т&lt;/em&gt; comes before &lt;em&gt;Ш&lt;/em&gt; in Cyrillic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;International Notation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In topology, an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/F%CF%83_set"&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(F_\sigma\)&lt;/span&gt; set&lt;/a&gt; is the countable union of closed sets and a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%CE%B4_set"&gt;&lt;span class="math"&gt;\(G_\delta\)&lt;/span&gt; set&lt;/a&gt; is the countable intersection of open sets. There is a mix of languages at play in this notation: the F stands for &lt;em&gt;fermé&lt;/em&gt; (closed in French) and the sigma for &lt;em&gt;somme&lt;/em&gt; (sum in French) while the G and delta stand for &lt;em&gt;Gebiet&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Durchschnitt&lt;/em&gt;, the German words for (in the context of set theory) open set and intersection respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mathoverflow.net/a/74013"&gt;It seems&lt;/a&gt; this notation was first introduced by Felix Hausdorff in his book &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grundz%C3%BCge_der_Mengenlehre"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grundzüge der Mengenlehre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (Basics of Set Theory):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"Wir bezeichnen abgeschlosssene Mengen, wie schon öfter, mit F (ensemble fermé), Gebiete mit G."&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
(&lt;a href="https://archive.org/stream/grundzgedermen00hausuoft#page/304/mode/2up"&gt;pg 304 of the first edition&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The use of both German and French in the notation brings to mind the international nature of mathematics (e.g. the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Congress_of_Mathematicians"&gt;International Congress of Mathematicians&lt;/a&gt;) at the beginning of the 20th century. Hausdorff's book was first published in April of 1914.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var align = "center",
        indent = "0em",
        linebreak = "false";

    if (false) {
        align = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "left" : align;
        indent = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? "0em" : indent;
        linebreak = (screen.width &lt; 768) ? 'true' : linebreak;
    }

    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = 'https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.0/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: '"+ align +"'," +
        "    displayIndent: '"+ indent +"'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    messageStyle: 'normal'," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['\\\\(','\\\\)'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'inherit ! important'} }," +
        "        linebreaks: { automatic: "+ linebreak +", width: '90% container' }," +
        "    }, " +
        "}); " +
        "if ('default' !== 'default') {" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('HTML-CSS Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax['HTML-CSS'].FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
            "MathJax.Hub.Register.StartupHook('SVG Jax Ready',function () {" +
                "var VARIANT = MathJax.OutputJax.SVG.FONTDATA.VARIANT;" +
                "VARIANT['normal'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default');" +
                "VARIANT['bold'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-bold');" +
                "VARIANT['italic'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
                "VARIANT['-tex-mathit'].fonts.unshift('MathJax_default-italic');" +
            "});" +
        "}";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="Russian"></category><category term="control theory"></category></entry><entry><title>Varken</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/varken.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-11T22:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-04-11T22:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-04-11:/varken.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Down to Earth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's featured word is &lt;em&gt;varken&lt;/em&gt;, the Dutch word for pig. Similarly, the Dutch word for pork is &lt;em&gt;varkensvlees&lt;/em&gt;  (pigs-meat).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another dutch word is &lt;em&gt;aarde&lt;/em&gt;, which means earth or soil. Planet Earth is &lt;em&gt;de Aarde&lt;/em&gt;. And earth makes an appearance in &lt;em&gt;aardappel&lt;/em&gt;, the Dutch word for potato …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Down to Earth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's featured word is &lt;em&gt;varken&lt;/em&gt;, the Dutch word for pig. Similarly, the Dutch word for pork is &lt;em&gt;varkensvlees&lt;/em&gt;  (pigs-meat).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another dutch word is &lt;em&gt;aarde&lt;/em&gt;, which means earth or soil. Planet Earth is &lt;em&gt;de Aarde&lt;/em&gt;. And earth makes an appearance in &lt;em&gt;aardappel&lt;/em&gt;, the Dutch word for potato (earth-apple).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd known both &lt;em&gt;aarde&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;varken&lt;/em&gt; for a while, but I only realized today that an aardvark (&lt;em&gt;aardvarken&lt;/em&gt; in Dutch) is simply an earth-pig. But isn't an earth-pig just a ground-hog? No, the Dutch word for groundhog is &lt;a href="https://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosmarmot"&gt;&lt;em&gt;bosmarmot&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (forest-marmot).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img alt="A very colorful marmot" src="https://yvanhuele.github.io/images/wow/stylish_marmot.png" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em style="font-size:90%"&gt;neither aardvark nor groundhog&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em style="font-size:90%"&gt;(probably a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hoary_marmot"&gt;hoary marmot&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Dutch"></category><category term="compound words"></category></entry><entry><title>Квітень</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/kviten.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-02T17:45:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-04-02T17:45:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-04-02:/kviten.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;April Flowers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's featured word is квітень, because I was too impatient to wait until November. Квітень (pronounced &lt;em&gt;kvee-teyn&lt;/em&gt;) is the Ukrainian name for the month of April. In Russian, the names of the months sound familiar: January is январь (&lt;em&gt;yan-var&lt;/em&gt;), April is апрель (&lt;em&gt;ap-ryel&lt;/em&gt;), and October is октябрь …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;April Flowers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's featured word is квітень, because I was too impatient to wait until November. Квітень (pronounced &lt;em&gt;kvee-teyn&lt;/em&gt;) is the Ukrainian name for the month of April. In Russian, the names of the months sound familiar: January is январь (&lt;em&gt;yan-var&lt;/em&gt;), April is апрель (&lt;em&gt;ap-ryel&lt;/em&gt;), and October is октябрь (&lt;em&gt;ok-tya-br&lt;/em&gt;). But in Ukrainian, the names of the months are totally different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was first learning the months of the year in Ukrainian, this unfamiliarity upset me. "Ukrainian months are so confusing!" I exclaimed in frustration to my partner, a native speaker of both Russian and Ukrainian. "On the contrary," she countered, "Ukrainian months are much easier to remember." What I didn't realize at the time was that the names of the months in Ukrainian are related to the time of year and human interactions with nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, квітень is derived from квітка, the Ukrainian word for flower. Similarly, травень, the Ukrainian word for May, is derived from трава, the word for grass. Other favorites include лютий (February) meaning harsh, червень (June) which could refer either to scale insects (червець) or the color red (червоний), and жовтень (October) from the color yellow (жовтий). But best of all is листопад (November) meaning the falling of leaves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explanations for the names of all twelve months &lt;a href="http://proudofukraine.com/ukrainian-calendar-and-names-of-the-months/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Ukrainian"></category><category term="calendars"></category></entry><entry><title>Тооел</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/tooel.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-26T18:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-03-26T18:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-03-26:/tooel.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Stranger in a Not-So-Strange Land&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently on a plane for the first time in a while. When clouds obscured the landscape below, I decided to engage with the screen in front of me. Prompted to choose a language I opted for one I don't know all that well …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Stranger in a Not-So-Strange Land&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was recently on a plane for the first time in a while. When clouds obscured the landscape below, I decided to engage with the screen in front of me. Prompted to choose a language I opted for one I don't know all that well (as has been my habit) — this time I chose Russian. True to form, I quickly decided I was lost and scrambled to switch back into English. However, instead of giving up altogether, I spent a little time memorizing the screen and then switched back into Russian. Using my newfound knowledge of the screen layout, I was able to navigate to the in-flight map and explore the now-foreign landscape of the Western United States. I tested my reading skills with the transliterations of Salt Lake City (Солт-Лейк-Сити), Ogden (Огден), and Provo (Прово), but had to supress a laugh when I reached Tooele.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img alt="In-flight map of Northern Utah" src="https://yvanhuele.github.io/images/wow/tooele.jpg" style="max-width:90%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Defiantly Unphonetic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tooele is the name of a city, county, and a valley in Northern Utah. The spelling is treacherous: Upon hearing the name &lt;em&gt;Tooele&lt;/em&gt; spoken out loud, you'd be forgiven for thinking it was spelled &lt;em&gt;Tuwilla&lt;/em&gt; instead. To add insult to injury, it &lt;a href="http://www.co.tooele.ut.us/clerk/information/tooele.pdf"&gt;seems the original spelling was Tuilla&lt;/a&gt;. Having tricked many people before, the unphonetic spelling certainly confused the Russian-language in-flight map, which offered the following transliteration: Тооел.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Words with double o's are rare in Russian, but there are a few examples such as сообщение (message) and зоопарк (zoo). Using the pronunciation of these words as a guide, it would follow that Тооел should be pronounced &lt;em&gt;tah-ah-el&lt;/em&gt; or even &lt;em&gt;tah-ah-yel&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Russian Clash with the West&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being confused by Tooele is an understandable mistake. However, the in-flight map commits a more serious transgression by failing to be self-consistent. Indeed, just north of Тооел, we find the transliterations of West Jordan and West Valley City. These are rendered as Уэст-Джордан (&lt;em&gt;Oo-est Djor-dan&lt;/em&gt;) and Вест-Вэлли-Сити (&lt;em&gt;Vest-Veh-lee See-tee&lt;/em&gt;), respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or perhaps the in-flight map is paying homage to &lt;a href="https://nameberry.com/blog/mormon-baby-names-traditions-and-trends"&gt;Utah's love of unconventional spellings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Russian"></category><category term="Cyrillic"></category><category term="Utah"></category><category term="fluff"></category></entry><entry><title>Догадок</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/dogadok.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-15T21:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-03-15T21:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-03-15:/dogadok.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Some Guesswork&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we'll look at the Russian word &lt;em&gt;догадок&lt;/em&gt; (transliteration &lt;em&gt;dogadok&lt;/em&gt;), which, in the context we're interested in, means &lt;em&gt;conjectures&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;guesswork&lt;/em&gt;. Our focus is really on the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Declension"&gt;declension&lt;/a&gt; of догадок (genitive plural) rather than its meaning: any Russian noun would do, but I chose that one because …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Some Guesswork&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we'll look at the Russian word &lt;em&gt;догадок&lt;/em&gt; (transliteration &lt;em&gt;dogadok&lt;/em&gt;), which, in the context we're interested in, means &lt;em&gt;conjectures&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;guesswork&lt;/em&gt;. Our focus is really on the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Declension"&gt;declension&lt;/a&gt; of догадок (genitive plural) rather than its meaning: any Russian noun would do, but I chose that one because this post is based on a guess or  conjecture — or possibly just an inkling. Here is the (not very precise) conjecture: the declension of Russian nouns after numbers is related to the fact that the variance scales with the mean in count distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Count Distributions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard McElreath brings up the relationship between the variance and the mean of a count distribution when introducing count models in his Winter 2015 &lt;a href="http://xcelab.net/rm/statistical-rethinking/"&gt;Statistical Rethinking&lt;/a&gt; lectures. He also describes how this relationship is reflected in human languages. The discussion relevant to this post begins &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BrchZeyo7cg&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=1h7m10s"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and continues for just over a minute:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;"This is a very important thing about count variables. All count distributions are like this: the variance inflates with the mean. And that's true in nature as well: the bigger the magnitude of a count the more uncertainty there is around the mean and that's a normal thing about counts. This is actually kind of embedded intuitively in the inate human counting system which is logarithmic [...] it's present in all human languages: one, few, many. Right, that's logarithmic because it's magnitudes and people intuitively — even if they're not numerate beyond one, few, many — understand that many is vaguer than few and few is vaguer than one, so the precision goes down as [the mean] goes up as well."&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Numbers and Declension&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This remark about one, few, and many got me thinking about &lt;a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Russian/Numbers#Use_of_numerals_in_context"&gt;declension of nouns after numbers&lt;/a&gt; in Russian. The rules can get somewhat complex so I want to focus on the simplest example: counting objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Basic Rule&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll start with the following rule which is not quite correct and refine it later: &lt;em&gt;When there is exactly one of an object, use the nominative singular. When there are two, three, or four of an object, use the genitive singular. When there are five or more, use the genitive plural.&lt;/em&gt; (Note that we have different cases for one, few, and many.) For example, we have&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;одна догадка (one guess, nominative singular)&lt;br /&gt;
две догадки (two guesses, genitive singular)&lt;br /&gt;
пять догадок (five guesses, genitive plural)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"One guess, two guesses, five guesses" is a faithful translation, but if we were to try and force the grammar upon the English translation, it might take the form of "one guess, two [instances] of guess, five [instances] of guesses." It may help to see how the nominative and genitive cases are used in another context:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Эта догадка такая же хорошая, как и любая другая. (This guess is as good as any other.)&lt;br /&gt;
Причина этой догадки неизвестна. (The reason for this conjecture is unknown.)&lt;br /&gt;
Случайность этих догадок поражает. (The randomness of these guesses is astounding.)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the form of the number preceding the noun and the &lt;a href="http://www.russianlessons.net/grammar/nouns_genitive.php"&gt;noun-ending&lt;/a&gt; itself depend on the gender of the noun, but the pattern of nominative singular, genitive singular, genitive plural is followed across all genders:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;один суп (one soup)&lt;br /&gt;
два супа (two soups)&lt;br /&gt;
пять супов (five soups)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;одна ворона (one crow)&lt;br /&gt;
две вороны (two crows)&lt;br /&gt;
пять ворон (five crows)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;одно слово (one word)&lt;br /&gt;
два слова (two words)&lt;br /&gt;
пять слов (five words)  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;The Catch&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far so good, we seem to have different rules for one, few (two, three, four), and many (five or more). However, rule described above only works as long as the objects number twenty or fewer. As soon as we hit twenty-one, we start over. Numbers ending in one (but not in eleven) take us back to the nominative singular:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;одна догадка (one guess)&lt;br /&gt;
двадцать одна догадка (twenty-one guesses)&lt;br /&gt;
сто девяносто одна догадка (one hundred ninety-one guesses)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, numbers ending in two, three, or four (but not in twelve, thirteen, or fourteen) are followed by nouns in the genitive singular. For all others, we're back at the genitive plural.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now that we know the full rule, is the conjecture still valid? Your guess is as good as mine.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Russian"></category><category term="grammar"></category></entry><entry><title>Ворона</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/vorona.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-08T13:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-03-08T13:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-03-08:/vorona.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week, our featured word is ворона, or maybe it's собака, or maybe it's корова, or maybe it's all three. These are the Russian words for crow, dog, and cow, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They figure in a short Soviet claymation film, Пластилиновая ворона (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plasticine_Crow"&gt;Plasticine Crow&lt;/a&gt;), based on Aesop's fable about the fox …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week, our featured word is ворона, or maybe it's собака, or maybe it's корова, or maybe it's all three. These are the Russian words for crow, dog, and cow, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They figure in a short Soviet claymation film, Пластилиновая ворона (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plasticine_Crow"&gt;Plasticine Crow&lt;/a&gt;), based on Aesop's fable about the fox and the crow. The narrator is uncertain about the details of the story so we are presented with multiple possiblities from the time of day, to the size of the cheese, to the identities of the main characters. Is it a crow or perhaps a dog or a cow? Is it a fox or is it instead a janitor/street-sweeper?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video is available &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/WVb_MKlsi1s"&gt;here on youtube&lt;/a&gt; and an English translation can be found &lt;a href="http://lyricstranslate.com/ru/mozhet-buit-vorona-%D0%B0-%D0%BC%D0%BE%D0%B6%D0%B5%D1%82-%D0%B1%D1%8B%D1%82%D1%8C-%D0%B2%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%BE%D0%BD%D0%B0-and-probably-crow.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img alt="stylized images of crows, a dog, and a cow" src="https://yvanhuele.github.io/images/wow/mozhet_byt.jpg" style="max-width:90%" /&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em style="font-size:90%"&gt;может быть ворона, а может быть собака, а может быть корова/ maybe a crow, or maybe a dog, or maybe a cow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me as a language learner, the cartoon strikes a good balance between structure and whimsy. You often get similar concepts together: the cheese might have been 200 grams, 300 grams, or half a kilo and might have been denstined for breakfast, lunch, or dinner. Presented together the relationships between these concepts are reinforced. 
On the other hand, the story sometimes takes you by surprise and introduces you to phrases you probably wouldn't encounter in other contexts: The fox might be an evil ostrich! And the moral of the story — not to horse around on construction sites — is an interesting alternative to the one presented in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Fontaine%27s_Fables"&gt;La Fontaine's version&lt;/a&gt; about the perils of being taken in by flattery. La Fontaine's version can be found translated into English &lt;a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=JW5bAAAAQAAJ&amp;amp;dq=Fables%20%20Denis&amp;amp;pg=PA83#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or set to music and performed live by Les Frères Jacques &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/d6Xp_uzxpeQ"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Though, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Fox_and_the_Crow_(Aesop)#The_story"&gt;apparently&lt;/a&gt; La Fontaine's moral was not always viewed as sufficiently moralizing by some who were scandalized that the fox was allowed to make off with his ill-gotten cheese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img alt="stylized cat" src="https://yvanhuele.github.io/images/wow/koshka.png" style="max-width:30%" /&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em style="font-size:90%"&gt;a new possibility for your consideration: а может быть это кошка&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sneak Preview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The images in this post offer a taste of an upcoming blog post. They were made using a style transfer algorithm to render photographs in the style of one of the frames from the Plasticine Crow.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Russian"></category><category term="cartoons"></category></entry><entry><title>Winkelwagen</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/winkelwagen.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-25T20:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-02-25T20:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-02-25:/winkelwagen.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What's Your Angle?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's word is the Dutch &lt;em&gt;winkelwagen&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;winkel&lt;/em&gt; means shop or store, &lt;em&gt;wagen&lt;/em&gt; means cart or car, and together they form a shopping cart. I found the sound of the word amusing and wanted to feature it for that reason alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was just going to leave …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What's Your Angle?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week's word is the Dutch &lt;em&gt;winkelwagen&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;em&gt;winkel&lt;/em&gt; means shop or store, &lt;em&gt;wagen&lt;/em&gt; means cart or car, and together they form a shopping cart. I found the sound of the word amusing and wanted to feature it for that reason alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was just going to leave it at that when I began to wonder about the word &lt;em&gt;winkel&lt;/em&gt;: The Ducth word for shop didn't seem to match any word for shop that I knew in other languages. To be fair, unlike the word market (Dutch: &lt;em&gt;markt&lt;/em&gt;; German: &lt;em&gt;Markt&lt;/em&gt;; French: &lt;em&gt;marché&lt;/em&gt;; Spanish: &lt;em&gt;mercado&lt;/em&gt;), the words for shop or store seem to vary a lot by language (German: &lt;em&gt;Geschäft&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Laden&lt;/em&gt;; French: &lt;em&gt;magazin&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;boutique&lt;/em&gt;; Spanish: &lt;em&gt;tienda&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Digging deeper, I learned that winkel &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/winkel#Etymology"&gt;once meant corner&lt;/a&gt;. Had I done any mathematics in German, I might have known that &lt;em&gt;Winkel&lt;/em&gt; is the German word for angle. Anyways, it seems that corner turned into corner store, then into store and lost its original meaning of corner (&lt;em&gt;hoek&lt;/em&gt; in modern Dutch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Periwinkle Periwinkles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winkel shares a common root with the English words &lt;em&gt;winch&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;wink&lt;/em&gt;.  These words also share a common root with one type of &lt;em&gt;periwinkle&lt;/em&gt;, but not with its homonym. We can split periwinkles into two categories: in one category is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_periwinkle"&gt;type of snail&lt;/a&gt; and in the other is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vinca"&gt;type of flower&lt;/a&gt; along with a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Periwinkle_(color)"&gt;color&lt;/a&gt; matching that of the flower. The snail is &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/periwinkle#Etymology_2"&gt;related&lt;/a&gt; to winking, but the flower &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/periwinkle#Etymology_1"&gt;is not&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Dutch"></category><category term="etymology"></category></entry><entry><title>Суп</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/sup.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-18T17:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T17:30:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-02-18:/sup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Big Cottonwood Soup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I experienced a bit of reverse culture shock. This was all the more surprising given that I had neither left my original cultural environment nor spent any significant amount of time emerged in the culture I had seemingly adopted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was waiting for the ski …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Big Cottonwood Soup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I experienced a bit of reverse culture shock. This was all the more surprising given that I had neither left my original cultural environment nor spent any significant amount of time emerged in the culture I had seemingly adopted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was waiting for the ski bus and looking over the posted schedule.  After checking the return times, my eyes were drawn to the route map. Upon reading the labels &lt;em&gt;Big Cottonwood Cyn&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Little Cottonwood Cyn&lt;/em&gt;, I did a double-take:  It took me a full ten seconds to realize that &lt;em&gt;cyn&lt;/em&gt; is the (English) abbreviation for canyon rather than &lt;em&gt;суп&lt;/em&gt;, the Russian word for soup. With italics, they're indistinguishable, so here they are again without emphasis: cyn vs суп. Despite the small difference, having once misread the sign, I cannot unsee the soup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cyn abbreviations in UTA ski bus map and Russian Wikipedia article on суп" src="https://yvanhuele.github.io/images/wow/cyn.png" style="max-width:90%" /&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em style="font-size:90%"&gt;Left: &lt;a href="https://www.rideuta.com/-/media/Files/Rider-Tools/System-Maps/2017/2017_skimap_justmap.ashx?la=en"&gt;UTA ski bus map&lt;/a&gt;. Right &lt;a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A1%D1%83%D0%BF"&gt;Russian Wikipedia article on soup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Opposite Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although this is the first time I've accidentally mistaken the Latin alphabet for Cyrillic, the opposite problem — reading Cyrillic characters as Latin ones — was very common when I first started learning Russian and Ukrainian and is a problem that continues to haunt me.  Many &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyrillic_alphabets#Common_letters"&gt;Cyrillic letters&lt;/a&gt; look the same as Latin letters but are pronounced differently. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;В/в sounds like V/v&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Н/н sounds like N/n&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Р/р sounds like R/r&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the more infamous examples is &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/pectopah"&gt;ресторан&lt;/a&gt; (restaurant, transliteration: &lt;em&gt;restoran&lt;/em&gt;), but others include север (north, transliteration: &lt;em&gt;sever&lt;/em&gt;), верх (up, transliteration: &lt;em&gt;verkh&lt;/em&gt;), and of course the СССР (USSR, which is surprisingly close to the transliteration: &lt;em&gt;SSSR&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Russian"></category><category term="Cyrillic"></category></entry></feed>