<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Salientia Stuff - Word of the Week</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/feeds/word-of-the-week.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://yvanhuele.github.io/</id><updated>2018-02-18T17:30:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Суп</title><link href="https://yvanhuele.github.io/sup.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-18T17:30:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-02-18T17:30:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Yannick</name></author><id>tag:yvanhuele.github.io,2018-02-18:/sup.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Big Cottonwood Soup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I experienced a bit of reverse culture shock. This was all the more surprising given that I had neither left my original cultural environment nor spent any significant amount of time emerged in the culture I had seemingly adopted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was waiting for the ski …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Big Cottonwood Soup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week, I experienced a bit of reverse culture shock. This was all the more surprising given that I had neither left my original cultural environment nor spent any significant amount of time emerged in the culture I had seemingly adopted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was waiting for the ski bus and looking over the posted schedule.  After checking the return times, my eyes were drawn to the route map. Upon reading the labels &lt;em&gt;Big Cottonwood Cyn&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Little Cottonwood Cyn&lt;/em&gt;, I did a double-take:  It took me a full ten seconds to realize that &lt;em&gt;cyn&lt;/em&gt; is the (English) abbreviation for canyon rather than &lt;em&gt;суп&lt;/em&gt;, the Russian word for soup. With italics, they're indistinguishable, so here they are again without emphasis: cyn vs суп. Despite the small difference, having once misread the sign, I cannot unsee the soup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;img alt="Cyn abbreviations in UTA ski bus map and Russian Wikipedia article on суп" src="https://yvanhuele.github.io/images/wow/cyn.png" style="max-width:90%" /&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em style="font-size:90%"&gt;Left: &lt;a href="https://www.rideuta.com/-/media/Files/Rider-Tools/System-Maps/2017/2017_skimap_justmap.ashx?la=en"&gt;UTA ski bus map&lt;/a&gt;. Right &lt;a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%A1%D1%83%D0%BF"&gt;Russian Wikipedia article on soup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Opposite Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although this is the first time I've accidentally mistaken the Latin alphabet for Cyrillic, the opposite problem — reading Cyrillic characters as Latin ones — was very common when I first started learning Russian and Ukrainian and is a problem that continues to haunt me.  Many &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyrillic_alphabets#Common_letters"&gt;Cyrillic letters&lt;/a&gt; look the same as Latin letters but are pronounced differently. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;В/в sounds like V/v&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Н/н sounds like N/n&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Р/р sounds like R/r&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the more infamous examples is &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/pectopah"&gt;ресторан&lt;/a&gt; (restaurant, transliteration: &lt;em&gt;restoran&lt;/em&gt;), but others include север (north, transliteration: &lt;em&gt;sever&lt;/em&gt;), верх (up, transliteration: &lt;em&gt;verkh&lt;/em&gt;), and of course the СССР (USSR, which is surprisingly close to the transliteration: &lt;em&gt;SSSR&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>